Finding Aid for Dale Haviland papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dale Haviland Papers
1964-1991
1970-1979
Haviland, Dale.
2014015 Aa 2
Correspondence and collected periodicals of Dale Haviland, resident of Brighton, Michigan. Haviland edited a libertarian newsletter A is A and other titles.
9 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Dale Haviland (donor no. 10994 ) in September 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
In the 1970s Brighton, Mich. resident Dale Haviland edited a libertarian newsletter A is A, and libertarian news and services catalog Mega Listings. He also compiled the 1972 Libertarian Periodicals Directory. Haviland and the A is A associate editors were engaged in correspondence with editors and compilers of other libertarian periodicals, as well as with the readers. Haviland published A is A Newsletter between 1971 and 1973, interrupted publication in 1974, and continued in 1975.
The Dale Haviland papers collection includes Haviland's correspondence and collected periodicals, pamphlets and catalogs used by Haviland to publish the A is A Newsletter, catalog of libertarian services and publications Mega Listings, and directories of libertarian press. The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Publications, and Collected Material.
Subjects:
Haviland, Dale.; Currency question--United States.; Free enterprise--Periodicals.; Individualism--Periodicals.; Libertarian literature.; Libertarian literature--Catalogs.; Libertarianism--Periodicals.; Libertarians--Directories.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.75 linear feet) includes Haviland's exchanges with readers of the A is A Newsletter and other libertarian publications, who suggested titles for inclusion in Haviland's directory of libertarian press and articles to reprint. Also included here is Haviland's correspondence with authors, compilers, editors, and publishers of libertarian periodicals and catalogs. Haviland kept separate folders to hold his exchanges with some individuals, but the majority of his correspondence was organized in alphabetical order. Named files include correspondence with Mitchell Jones, editor of The New Individualist, Ralph Fucetola III, one of the editors of The Abolitionist, William Van Doren, The Diode editor and publisher; among others.
  - Baker, Robert P. (Box 1)
  - Bardon, Kerry (Box 1)
  - Block, Walter (Box 1)
  - Brady, Mark (Box 1)
  - Branden, Nathaniel (Box 1)
  - Browne, Harry (Box 1)
  - Castorina, Camille (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Mark (Box 1)
  - Courtney, Ron (Box 1)
  - Curly, Charles (Box 1)
  - Den Uyl, Doug (Box 1)
  - Ditko, Steve (Box 1)
  - Drummond, Karen (Box 1)
  - Eenigenburg, Brian (Box 1)
  - Foley, Tim (Box 1)
  - Fucetola, Ralph III (Box 1)
  - Geisingler, Eric L. (Box 1)
  - Greenberg, Gary (Box 1)
  - Hospers, John (Box 1)
  - Jones, Mitchell (Box 1)
  - Knight, Jesse F. (Box 1)
  - Machan, Tibor (Box 1)
  - May, Janet (Box 1)
  - McAlpine, Peter E. (Box 1)
  - McConahy, Malcolm (Box 1)
  - Merrill, Ronald (Box 1)
  - Morris, Joseph A. (Box 1)
  - Murphy, Neil (Box 1)
  - Myers, Rob (Box 1)
  - Nichols, Rosalie (Box 1)
  - Odell, Barry K. (Box 1)
  - Perkins, Ernestine and Richard (Box 1)
  - Riggs, Guy (Box 1)
  - Shields, Jay (Box 1)
  - Sharp, Mike (Box 1)
  - Silver, Bernie and Frank, Diane (Box 1)
  - Strauss, Erwin S. (Box 1)
  - Stuhr, Ken (Box 1)
  - Susel, William (Box 1)
  - Symms. Steven (Box 1)
  - Tunnwhill, Morris G. (Box 1)
  - Van Doren, William (Box 1)
  - Varnell, Paul O. (Box 1)
  - Watner, Carl (Box 1)
  - Wright, Brian (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, A-Z, 7 folders (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series (7.4 linear feet) is the heart of the collection. It is divided into three groups: Periodicals, Publications and Services Catalogs, and Pamphlets. The Periodicals is the largest of the three (7 linear feet) and includes the entire run of Haviland's A is A Newsletter. The majority of the periodicals found in the collection are U.S.-published, with a few exceptions, mostly published in the U.K. A great number of these periodicals are quite obscure and rare, in some cases hand- or typewritten on typewriters, with a few scattered issues in existence: Preform Inform, Vonulife, Atlantis Review; while others have been published for years: Imprimis, New Libertarian Notes, Southern Libertarian Messenger; among others. In some cases folders contain a small amount of correspondence related to publication. Some material has Haviland's comments.
  - Periodicals
    - A is A Newsletter, 1971-1973; 1975 (Box 2)
      (Brighton, Mich.: Mega, Dale Haviland, editor)
    - Abolitionist, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      (New Jersey)
    - Account, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
      (Menlo Park, CA)
    - Agorafund, 1971 (Box 2)
      (Surrey, UK)
    - American-African Affairs Association, 1960-1970 (Box 2)
      (New York)
    - Arbiter, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      (Mill Valley, CA)
    - Ark, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      (Hichory, N.C.)
    - ATCOPS Reporter, 1974; 1977-1980 (Box 2)
      (Saugerties, NY)
    - Atlantis Enterprises
      (see also IREC Enterprises)
      - Atlantis News, 1968-1972; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Atlantis Review, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
        (Atlantis Enterprises)
    - Behind the Scenes in Washington, 1978 (Box 2)
      (Provo, UT)
    - CaLiber, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      (Los Angeles, CA)
    - Canada Month, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
      (Montreal, Que.)
    - Castalian, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Center for Libertarian Studies, 1971 (Box 2)
      (Houston, TX)
    - Central Michigan University Students for Objectivism Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      (Mt. Pleasant, MI)
    - Chicago Rap, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Commentary on Liberty, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      (Philadelphia, PA)
    - Constitutionalist, 1984 (Box 2)
      (Dearborn, MI)
    - Davis Arena, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      (Davis, CA)
    - De Young Press, 1972 (Box 2)
      (St. Paul, MN)
    - Detroit Banner, 1972 (Box 2)
      (Detroit, MI)
    - Diode, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
      (Baltimore, MD)
    - Dollars & Sense, 1971-1974; 1979; undated (Box 2)
      (Washington, D.C.)
    - Douglas MacArthur Digest, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Efficacy, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Fire Bringer, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
      (Colorado Springs, CO)
    - Focus, 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - Free Earth Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      (Philadelphia, PA.)
      (see also SOL III Magazine)
    - Free Libertarian, 1973-1974; 1976 (Box 2)
      (New York, NY)
    - Free Market, 1991 (Box 2)
      (Auburn, AL)
    - Free Press Network, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      (Apple Valley, CA)
    - Freedom, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
      (St. Hill Manor, England)
    - Freedom & Union, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Freedom First, 1970 (Box 2)
      (London, England)
    - Freedom Review, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
      (Watford, U.K.)
    - Freeman: Ideas on Liberty, 1969-1977; 4 folders (Box 3)
      (Irvington-on-Hudson, NY)
    - Gadfly, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      (Ferndale, MI)
    - Gold Bug, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Gold Newsletter, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
      (New Orleans, LA)
    - Green Egg, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      (St. Louis, MO)
    - Green Revolution, 1970 (Box 3)
      (Freeland, MD)
    - Hard Core News, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Harris County Libertarian Party Newsletter, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Hundred Against One, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      (Toronto, Canada)
    - Idaho Compass, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      (Caldwell, ID)
    - Ignition, April 1970 (Box 3)
      (Denver, CO)
    - Imprimis, 1972-1988; 8 folders (Box 4)
      (Hillsdale, MI)
    - Independent Libertarian Commentary, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      (Staten Island, NY)
    - Individual Liberty, 1974 (Box 4)
      (Warminster, PA)
    - Individualist, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
      (London, England?)
    - Individualist, 1972; 2 folders (Box 4)
      (Silver Spring, MD)
    - Infra Free Enterprise Trends, 1969-1971; 3 folders (Box 4)
      (Stockholm, Sweden)
    - Innovator, 1965-1969; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Integrator, July 1972 (Box 4)
      (Berkeley, CA)
    - Integrity, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      (Garfield, NJ)
    - IREC Enterprises
      (New York, NY and Cambridge, MA)
      (see also Atlantis Enterprises)
      - Enquiry, 1967 (Box 4)
      - IREC Review, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Invictus, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 5)
      (Rosemead, CA)
    - JAG, 1971-1974 (Box 5)
      (Oelwein, IA)
    - Law & Liberty, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
    - LeFevre's Journal, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
      (Orange, CA)
    - Liberator, February 1970 (Box 5)
      (Claremont, CA)
    - Liberator, 1970 (Box 5)
      (Iowa City, IA)
    - Libertarian, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
      (Wenonah, NJ)
    - Libertarian Alternative, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
      (San Diego, CA)
    - Libertarian Analysis, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Libertarian Connection, 1969-1973; 12 folders (Box 5)
    - Libertarian Forum, 1969-1974; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Libertarian Party of Canada News, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
    - Libertarian Party of Michigan Newsletter, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
      (Rochester, MI)
    - Libertas, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      (Santa Ana, CA)
    - Life and Liberty, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      (North Plainfield, NJ)
    - LP News scattered issues, 1974-1980 (Box 6)
      (various places of publication)
    - Manas, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Metro Magazine, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
      (Atlanta, GA)
    - Michigan Libertarian scattered issues, 1975-1987 (Box 6)
    - Mike Freeman
      - Preform Inform, 1965; 1968-1971 (Box 6)
        (Santa Monica, CA)
      - Vonulife, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        (Grants Pass, OR)
      - Vonulife, 1973 (Box 6)
        (Paradise, CA)
      - Vonulink, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
        (Cave Junction, OR)
    - Minus One, 1971-1974 (Box 6)
    - New Capitalist, 1971 (Box 6)
    - New Individualist, 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 6)
      (Austin, TX)
    - New Libertarian Notes, 1972-1974; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - New Schools Exchange Newsletter, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Ohio Libertarian, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      (Bedford, OH)
    - Option, 1973-1975 (Box 6)
    - Outlook, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Partisan, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Pegasus, 1972 (Box 6)
      (Cochituate, MA)
    - Premise, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      (Asbury Park, NJ)
    - Quillon, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      (Detroit (?), MI)
    - Rampart College Newsletter, 1971-1974 (Box 6)
    - Rational Focus, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      (Akron, OH)
    - Religion and Society (Box 6)
      (see St. Croix Review)
    - Right Angle, 1973 (Box 6)
      (Harper Woods, MI)
    - Rip-off Resistance, 1973 (Box 6)
      (Bountiful, UT)
    - Schism, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      (Mt. Vernon, OH)
    - Self Reliance, 1971 (Box 6)
      (Richmond, VA)
      (see also Libertarian Enterprises Book Catalogs)
    - Skeptic, 1971 (Box 6)
      (place of publication not identified)
    - Society for Individual Liberty
      - Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 6)
      - SIL News, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - Various publications (Box 6)
    - SOL III Magazine, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 7)
      (see also Free Earth Magazine)
    - Southern Libertarian Messenger with gaps, 1972-1982; 2 folders (Box 7)
      (Florence, SC)
    - Southern Libertarian Review, 1974 (Box 7)
      (Arlington, VA)
    - St. Croix Review 1973-1974 scattered, 1976-1979, 1973-1979 (Box 7)
      (Stillwater, MN)
    - Starboard, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
      (Southgate, MI)
    - Tax Rebel News, 1977 (Box 7)
      (Howell, MI)
    - Thorn, 1970 (Box 7)
      (Ann Arbor, MI)
    - Thought, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
      (Winchester, MA)
    - Tidewater College Journal, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Torch, 1969-1972; 2 folders (Box 7)
      (Grove City, PA)
    - Unbound!, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
      (Boston, MA)
    - Vanguard, 1971 (Box 7)
      (Lakewood, OH)
    - Views, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
      (published by Metropolitan Young Republican Club, place of publication not identified)
    - Volition, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      (Bismark, ND)
    - West World Review
      (Culver City, CA)
      - Western World Review, 1970-1974 (Box 7)
      - Western World Review Newsletter, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - World Research INK (Box 8)
    - Zeitgeist, 1972-1973 (Box 8)
      (Oak Park, IL)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Publications and services catalogs
    The Publications and Services group (0.15 linear feet) mostly contains libertarian book catalogs; also directories of periodicals and advertisements of audio-visual resources.
    - A is A
      - Mega Listings, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Libertarian Periodicals Directory, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Academic Associates Book News, 1969-1973 (Box 8)
      (Los Angeles, CA.)
    - Books for Libertarians, 1972-1974 (Box 8)
    - Cato Institute, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Duck Book Digest, 1982 (Box 8)
      (Cocoa, FL)
    - Free Market, 1970-1973 (Box 8)
    - Human Events (Box 8)
    - Infomat, 1971; 1973 (Box 8)
      (Verdes Estates, CA)
    - Laissez Faire, 1973; 1975; 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - Libertarian Buyers Guide, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Libertarian Enterprises Book Catalogs, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Libertarian Review, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Liberty, 1980 (Box 8)
      (Sunnyvale, CA)
    - Liberty Coin Service, 1971 (Box 8)
      (Lansing, MI)
    - SIL Services Bulletin, 1970-1971 (Box 8)
    - World Research Inc. (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Pamphlets
    Among pamphlets (0.25 linear feet) researchers will find published speeches and essays on various subjects, as well as periodical series of pamphlets.
    - A is A Libertarian Directory, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Bramble MiniBooks, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    - Center for Independent Education (Box 8)
    - De Jan Institute, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Fall Notes, 1973; 1983 (Box 8)
    - Institute for Humane Studies, 1968-1979 (Box 8)
    - Peace Plans, 1965-1971 (Box 9)
    - Rampart College, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Research Centre for Monetary and Financial Freedom, 1976 (Box 9)
    - S-3 Educational Series, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
      (SOL III)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
- Collected Material
  The Collected Material series (0.75 linear feet) includes mailings, correspondence, flyers, announcements of libertarian political organizations and clubs, educational institutions, and student organizations. Material present in this series indicates Haviland's interest in independent education and campus activism. Also present here are subject files with collected material about Ayn Rand, Ron Paul, and Edith Efron, among others, as well as collected essays, unpublished papers and articles on subjects such as objectivism, free enterprise, currency, economics, education, etc.
  - Libertarian National Convention, 1973 (Box 9)
  - American Economic Foundation (Box 9)
    (includes 33 1/3 rpm vinyl record)
  - Ayn Rand, Objectivism (Box 9)
  - Ayn Rand Society of Detroit (Box 9)
    (see also Detroit Society for Objectivism)
  - Articles, reports, research papers (Box 9)
  - Bantam Lecture Bureau (Box 9)
  - Campus Studies Institute (Box 9)
  - Center for Independent Education (Box 9)
    (Institute for Humane Studies)
  - Center for Libertarian Studies (Box 9)
  - Detroit Students for Objectivism (Box 9)
    (see also Ayn Rand Society of Detroit)
  - Discussion Club, St. Louis, MO (Box 9)
  - Efron, Edith (Box 9)
  - Flint School, Sarasota, FL (Box 9)
  - Free Enterprises Association (Box 9)
  - George Mason Movement (Box 9)
  - Institute to Economic Studies (Box 9)
  - Institute for Humane Studies (Box 9)
    (see also Center for Independent Education)
  - Institute for Libertarian Studies (Box 9)
  - John Birch Society (Box 9)
  - John Ziegler, Inc. (Box 9)
  - League of Non-Voters (Box 9)
  - Ludvig Von Mises Institute (Box 9)
  - Michigan Young Americans (Box 9)
  - Midwest Society of New Intellectuals (Box 9)
  - Paul, Ron (Box 9)
  - Speak Out! (Box 9)
  - Various organizations and miscellaneous (Box 9)
Related Material
Collections of Michigan libertarian newsletters from the holdings of the Bentley Historical Library: Libertarian Party of Lapeer/Genesee County newsletters, Libertarian Party of Oakland County newsletters, Libertarian Party of Wayne County newsletters, Libertarian Party of West Michigan newsletters, Macomb County Libertarian Party newsletters, Metro-Detroit Libertarian newsletters.
Individual Michigan periodical titles: Full disclosure, 1997; The Grass Roots Journal, 1990-1991, also available at the University of Michigan Special Collections Library; The Michigan Libertarian, 1986-2006 and 1975-2011 (DVD); MWM Libertarian, 1997; The Truth, November-December 1996; Voice of Liberty, 1995-1996; and Washtenaw Libertarian, 1990-2007.
Also Responsible Enterprise Association Educational Foundation records, 1945-1972 (0.1 linear feet).